Council on the Continuing Education Unit (CCEU) Records
Council on the Continuing Education Unit (CCEU) Records
1968-1992
Council on the Continuing Education Unit
14.5 linear ft.
Contains operational and published material from the Council on the Continuing Education Unit, including papers, articles, meeting minutes, drafts, correspondence, and conference proceedings.
2458666
Biographical History
Originally formed as a National Task Force on continuing education commissioned by the Bureau of Education (now the Department of Education) in 1968, the Council on the Continuing Education Unit (CCEU) gathered academic, business and education experts from around the country to define and promote the use of a single consistent unit of measurement for continuing education. Participants included representatives from health care, engineering, accounting, academia and many other professions. The result was the Continuing Education Unit, or CEU, defined as "ten contact hours of participation in an organized continuing education experience under responsible, qualified direction and instruction." The purpose of the CEU was to enable tracking and record-keeping of non-credit education undertaken by adult students. The CCEU formulated and disseminated guidelines on the use of the CEU and sponsored several conferences. The Council exists today (April 2006) as the International Association for Continuing Education and Training (IACET).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Council on the Continuing Education Unit (CCEU) Records consists of administrative files from the Council as well as the files of three of the Council's members: Keith Glancy, John Rhodes, and William Turner.
Administrative files contains articles of incorporation, membership lists, photos of the officers and directors of the CCEU, and various reports and surveys produced by the Council.
Proposals includes proposals made to the U.S. Office of Education, the Carnegie Corporation, the Kellogg Foundation, and the Exxon Education Foundation for various aspects of the Council's activities. Detailed information on one such activity is included in the National Task Force Pilot Project 1970-1971 material. History of the CEU is also included.
Meetings and minutes contains detailed meeting minutes for CCEU executive committees, working committees, board of directors, and annual meetings, as well as for other meetings in which CCEU members participated or at which they presented, such as the Indiana Nurses' Association conference on the CEU, the Maryland Project to Strengthen Community Services and Continuing Education, the Iowa Conference on the CEU, and several CCEU annual conferences. Correspondence-subject files further document the activities of the CCEU by including correspondence from Glancy, Rhodes and Turner on task force and council activities. Also included here are a number of files from John Rhodes that cover a variety of CEU-related activities of which he was a part, such as the University System of Georgia's Ad Hoc Subcommittees on the CEU and on the External Degree Program, the CEU guidelines committee, an interesting list of predictions concerning the CEU, work on methods reporting CEUs, and more.
Publications of the CCEU, ordered chronologically to highlight the evolution of the CEU, includes papers, reports, presentations, statements and other material officially issued by, or under the auspices of, the Council. Papers and Articles encompasses CEU-related material written and/or published by other bodies such as the American Nurses' Association, the Illinois Community College Board. Also found here are papers written by Council members (including Glancy, Rhodes and Turner) that were not official CCEU publications. The last segment of this series contains papers and articles concerned with adult or continuing education, but not necessarily with the CEU per se.
Principles and Practices includes guidelines and policies regarding the CEU, issued by various professional bodies for their members. Academic, professional and recreational organizations are represented, among others the American Bankers Association, the American Hospital Association, the Boy Scouts of America, Indiana University, the Ordre des Ingenieurs du Quebec, the University of Colorado, and Whirlpool Corporation.
Proceedings contains the official proceedings from continuing education and CEU conferences, including the first five occurrences of the Annual Conference of the Council on the Continuing Education Unit.
Research reports comprises experiences with continuing education or the CEU, such as Ellen Corkery's "Mandatory Continuing Education in the Nursing Profession: Four States' Experience" (May 1986), while Miscellaneous contains a variety of continuing education or CEU-related brochures, pamphlets and booklets as well as four doctoral dissertations on aspects of the Continuing Education Unit.
Arrangement of the Collection
Because the collection encompasses the development and refinement of the CEU, where appropriate the material is ordered chronologically so that changes over time are more evident. Chronologically ordered series include Proposals, Meetings and minutes, Publications of the CCEU, and Proceedings. Other series are ordered alphabetically; this includes Administrative files, National Task Force Pilot Project 1970-1971, Correspondence-subject files, Papers and Articles, Principles and Practices, and Research reports.
Where possible, material which originally came from a particular individual is so noted in square brackets, for example "Continuing Education Council [John Rhodes files]" so that annotations in the material or handwritten notes can be traced to their author.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Andrews, Grover J.; Glancy, Keith.; Grogan, Paul J.; Rhodes, John A. Jr.; Turner, William L.; Association for Continuing Higher Education (U.S.); Council on the Continuing Education Unit.; International Association for Continuing Education and Training.; National Task Force on the Continuing Education Unit.; Adult education -- Research.; Continuing education.; Articles.; Brochures.; Correspondence.; Dissertations.; Drafts (documents); Leaflets.; Meeting minutes.; Notes (documents); Proposals.; Adult education teachers.; Teachers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Keith Glancy, Executive Director of the Council on the Continuing Education Unit
Inventory
- Administrative files
  - Articles of incorporation and bylaws (Box 1)
  - CCEU 501(c)3 application, 1977; 1980 (Box 1)
  - Certification mark, 1973; 1979,; 1981,; 1986 (Box 1)
  - CEU: calculating full-time equivalent, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Employer identification number, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Members of the council, 1978-1986 (Box 1)
  - Members by organization, 1985; 1986,; 1987 (Box 1)
  - Membership criteria, undated (Box 1)
  - Misapplication of the CCEU, 1981; 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - National Task Force members and CCEU officers and directors, 1978-1988; undated (Box 1)
  - National Task Force and CCEU directors' photographs (Box 1)
  - Organization manuals, 1980-1984; 1986 (Box 1)
  - Principles of Good Practice
    See also Meetings and minutes: Other meetings and presentations: National Conference on Principles of Good Practice (Wingspread Conference); Publications of the CCEU: Principles of Good Practice in Continuing Education (CCEU); Papers and Articles: About the CEU: Collins, Michael. "Some Further Thoughts on Principles of Good Practice in Continuing Education"
    - Chase Manhattan printing/special edition distribution list, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
    - Endorsements, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Slide/tape presentation, 1984; undated (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Annual activities reports, 1980-1985; 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Annual activities reports, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Council office activities, undated; includes Executive Director job description (Box 2)
    - Committee on Surveys and Research, 1980-1988; 8 folders (Box 2)
    - Executive Director monthly reports, 1984-1987 (Box 2)
    - Health professions task force, 1983; 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - National Task Force status report, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - Research and Planning Committee Annual Report, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Surveys (Box 2)
    - CEU survey, 1977 (Box 2)
    - CEU user survey (ASTD), 1979 (Box 2)
    - CEU user survey, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Computer resources survey, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Assessment survey, 1988 (Box 2)
- Proposals (Box 2)
  - - National Task Force on the CEU: Proposal to the U.S. Office of Education, 1971 (Box 2)
  - - Council on the CEU: "A Two-Phase Proposal for the National Implementation of the Continuing Education Unit", 1972 (Box 2)
  - - Council on the CEU: Proposal to the Fund for the Improvement of Post-Secondary Education, 1977 (Box 2)
  - - Council on the CEU: Proposal to the Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1978 (Box 2)
  - - Council on the CEU: Proposal to Exxon Education Foundation, 1978 (Box 2)
  - - Council on the CEU: Proposal to the W.K. Kellog Foundation, 1982 (Box 2)
- National Task Force Pilot Project, 1970-1971
  - Evaluation reports, 2 folders (Box 3)
    See also Publications of the CCEU: "The Continuing Education Unit: Pilot Project Report" (Glancy, Keith)
  - Indiana University (Box 3)
  - North Carolina State University (Box 3)
  - Rutgers University (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University (Box 3)
  - University Center for Adult Education, Detroit (Box 3)
  - University of California at Los Angeles (Box 3)
  - University of Illinois (Box 3)
  - University of Iowa (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan (Box 3)
  - University of Minnesota (Box 3)
  - University of New Hampshire (Box 3)
  - University of Washington (Box 3)
  - West Virginia University (Box 3)
- History
  - "History and Highlights in the Development of the Continuing Education Unit" (Turner, William L.), undated (Box 4)
  - "National Task Force: 1972 Discussion" (Glancy, Keith E., editor) (Box 4)
- Meetings and minutes
  - CCEU meetings
    - "Planning conference on the feasibility of a uniform crediting and certification system for continuing education", 1968 (Box 4)
      See also Publications of the CCEU: "Concept Paper for a Planning Conference to Study the Feasibility of a Uniform Crediting and Certification System for Continuing Education" (NUEA)
    - Task Force on the CEU, 1968-1977
      - Initial meeting, 1968 Oct 15 (Box 4)
      - Meeting minutes, 1969-1977; 28 folders (Box 4)
        A few meetings include other organizations:
        "The Continuing Education Unit: An Interim Report" (20 Oct 1970)
        Task Force on the CEU and National University Extension Association (NUEA) Policy Committee (12 Aug 1974)
        Task Force on the CEU and Conference on the CEU in Business, Industry and Government (8-9 Dec 1975)
        Task Force on the CEU with Educational Testing Service (27-28 Jan 1977)
        Task Force on the CEU with Educational Testing Service (31 Mar 1977)
    - Working committee: CCEU and NUEA, 1977 Jun (Box 4)
    - Working committee: CCEU and Educational Testing Service, 1977 Jul (Box 4)
    - Task Force on the CEU and Council on the CEU (CCEU), 1977 Aug-Oct; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Council on the CEU (CCEU) meetings, 1977-1987; meetings include those of executive committees, working committees, board of directors, and annual meetings
      - Minutes, 1977 Dec - 1980 Jun; 16 folders (Box 5)
      - Minutes, 1980 Jun - 1983 Feb; 16 folders (Box 6)
      - Minutes, 1983 Jun - 1986 Mar; 19 folders (Box 7)
      - Minutes, 1986 Jun - 1987 Jun; 7 folders (Box 8)
  - Other meetings and presentations
    - National University Extension Association, 1971 (Box 8)
    - Georgia Sub-committee on External Degree, 1972 (Box 8)
      See also Correspondence-subject files: Other: External Degree program [John Rhodes files]
    - Indiana Nurses' Association: "A Conference to Discuss the Continuing Education Unit", 1972 (Box 8)
    - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1972 (Box 8)
    - University Council on Education for Public Responsibility: National Conference, 1973 (Box 8)
    - Virginia Nurses' Association, 1973 (Box 8)
    - Georgia Tech University, 1974 (Box 8)
    - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools: "A Conference on the Continuing Education Unit", 1974 (Box 8)
    - Maryland Project to Strengthen Community Services and Continuing Education, 1974 (Box 9)
    - National University Extension Association [John Rhodes files], 1974; 1975 (Box 9)
    - New England Center for Continuing Education, 1975 (Box 9)
    - Pennsylvania Library Association, 1976 (Box 9)
    - "The Continuing Education Unit in Business, Industry, Government, Unions, Associations and Professional Societies", 1976 (Box 9)
    - American Society for Training and Development, 1978 (Box 9)
    - National Invitational Conference on Continuing Education for Allied Health Professions, 1978 (Box 9)
      See also Proceedings: National Invitational Conference on Continuing Education for Health Professions
    - Iowa Conference on the CEU, 1979 (Box 9)
    - American Society for Engineering Education 87th Annual Conference, 1979 (Box 9)
    - Association for Continuing Higher Education: "CEU: The Pros and Cons", 1979 (Box 9)
    - 5th Annual Conference, Council for Noncollegiate Continuing Education, 1979 (Box 9)
    - Invitational Conference on Certification, 1981; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - National Project on Counseling Older People (Pilot Workshop), 1980 (Box 9)
    - University of Puerto Rico: "First State Conference on Continuing Education", 1981 (Box 9)
    - Conference on the CEU (Montreal), 1981 (Box 9)
    - CCEU 3rd Annual Conference, 1981 (Box 9)
      See also Proceedings: Third Annual Conference of the Council on the Continuing Education Unit
    - CCEU 4th Annual Conference, 1982 (Box 10)
      See also Proceedings: Fourth Annual Conference of the Council on the Continuing Education Unit
    - Graphic Arts Institute of America, 1983 (Box 10)
    - CCEU 5th Annual Conference, 1983 (Box 10)
      See also Proceedings: Fifth Annual Conference of the Council on the Continuing Education Unit
    - Invitational Conference on Standards, 1983 (Box 10)
    - National Conference on Principles of Good Practice (Wingspread Conference), 1984; 4 folders (Box 10)
      See also Princples of Good Practice
    - School of Public Health, Johns Hopkins University, 1985 (Box 10)
    - Association for Continuing Higher Education, 1985 (Box 10)
    - Adult Learners and National Priorities, 1985 (Box 10)
    - Iowa Conference on Mandatory Continuing Education, 1987 (Box 10)
- Correspondence-subject files
  - CEU task force and council
    - National Task Force on the CEU
      - Glancy, Keith E., 1970-1977; 8 folders (Box 11)
      - Grogan, Paul J., 1976 (Box 11)
      - Rhodes, John, 1971-1977; undated; 5 folders (Box 12)
      - Turner, William L., 1968-1976; 4 folders (Box 12)
      - Turner, William L., 1977 (Box 13)
    - National Task Force on the CEU & CCEU
      - Glancy, Keith E., 1977 (Box 13)
      - Turner, William L., 1977 (Box 13)
    - Council on the CEU
      - Glancy, Keith E., Jan 1978-May 1979; 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Glancy, Keith E., Jun 1979-1981; 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Rhodes, John, 1978-1980; 4 folders (Box 14)
      - Rhodes, John, 1981-1982; undated; 3 folders (Box 15)
      - Turner, William L., 1978-1979; 4 folders (Box 15)
      - Turner, William L., Jan 1980-Jun 1984; 8 folders (Box 16)
      - Turner, William L., Jul 1984-Dec 1987; 8 folders (Box 17)
  - Other
    - American Medical Association, 1974 (Box 18)
    - Carnegie Unit [John Rhodes files] (Box 18)
    - CCEU logo and criteria for use, 1974; 1979 (Box 18)
    - CCEU regional meetings [John Rhodes files], 1972-1973; undated (Box 18)
    - CEU, Ad Hoc Subcommittee on [John Rhodes files], 1971-1973; undated; 3 folders (Box 18)
    - CEU criteria and guidelines [John Rhodes files], 1973; draft copy w/annotations (Box 18)
    - CEU data bank proposal [John Rhodes files], 1972; 2 folders (Box 18)
      See also Papers and Articles: About the CEU: Darmstaetter, Josephine and Sanford, Robert. "The NFLPN CEU Data Bank Report: First Report"
    - CEU guidelines committee [John Rhodes files], 1972; undated; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - CEU guidelines committee [John Rhodes files], undated; 3 folders (Box 19)
    - CEU workshop [John Rhodes files], 1972 (Box 19)
    - Classification of continuing education units [John Rhodes files], undated (Box 19)
    - Continuing Education Commission [John Rhodes files], 1974 (Box 19)
    - Continuing Education Council [John Rhodes files], 1975 (Box 19)
    - Criteria for awarding the CEU [John Rhodes files], undated (Box 19)
    - External Degree program [John Rhodes files], 1972; 2 folders (Box 19)
      See also Other meetings and presentations: Georgia Sub-committee on External Degree
    - Formula review study team [John Rhodes files], 1972; undated; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Georgia Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admissions Officers [John Rhodes files], 1972-1973 (Box 19)
    - Individual Education Account [William L. Turner files], 1983-1984; 2 folders (Box 20)
      See also Papers and Articles: About the CEU: Lindberg, David S. "I.E.U. - C.E.U."
    - Louisiana State University [John Rhodes files], undated (Box 20)
    - Memphis State University [John Rhodes files], 1974-1975 (Box 20)
    - Predictions concerning the CEU [John Rhodes files], undated (Box 20)
    - Reporting CEUs [John Rhodes files], 1972; undated; 8 folders (Box 20)
    - Review of literature [John Rhodes files], undated (Box 20)
    - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools grant proposal [John Rhodes files], undated (Box 20)
    - Standard Nine Study questionnaire [John Rhodes files], undated (Box 20)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia [John Rhodes files], 1972 (Box 20)
    - Tennessee Higher Education Commission [John Rhodes files], 1974; 1976,; undated (Box 20)
    - Tennessee Workshop on Standard IX and the CEU [John Rhodes files], May 1974 (Box 21)
      See also Proceedings: Proceedings of the Tennessee Workshop on Standard IX and the CEU
    - University of Wisconsin-Extension [John Rhodes files], 1973-1975 (Box 21)
    - Western Interstate Commission on Higher Education [John Rhodes files], 1970 (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous [John Rhodes files], 1975; 1977,; undated (Box 21)
- Publications of the CCEU
  - "A Proposal to Develop a Uniform Unit of Measurement for Noncredit Continuing Education Programs" (Pitchell, Robert J.), 1968 (Box 21)
  - "Concept Paper for a Planning Conference to Study the Feasibility of a Uniform Crediting and Certification System for Continuing Education" (NUEA), 1968 (Box 21)
    See also Meetings and minutes: CCEU meetings: "Planning conference on the feasibility of a uniform crediting and certification system for continuing education"
  - Report of National Planning Group to Study the Feasibility of a Uniform Crediting and Certification System for Continuing Education (Turner, William L.)", 1968 (Box 21)
  - "Attempt Being Made to Provide Measure for Continuing Education" (National Task Force), 1968; news release (Box 21)
  - "Needed: A Uniform Unit to Measure One's Continuing Education" (Turner, William L.), 1968 (Box 21)
  - "A Uniform Unit of Measurement for Noncredit Continuing Education Programs: Background Information" (National Task Force), 1968 (Box 21)
  - "Elements of a System for the Uniform Measurement of Participation in Noncredit Continuing Education (Turner, William L.), 1969 (Box 21)
  - "An Interim Statement of the National Task Force" (National Task Force), 1970 (Box 21)
  - "Interim Report to National Planning Committee" (Turner, William L.), 1970 (Box 21)
  - "The Continuing Education Unit: A Uniform Unit of Measurement for Noncredit Continuing Education Programs" (Turner, William L.), 1970 (Box 21)
  - "The Continuing Education Unit: Pilot Project Report" (Glancy, Keith), 1971 (Box 21)
    See also National Task Force Pilot Project
  - "Status Report to Correspondents on Continuing Education Unit" (Glancy, Keith), 1971 (Box 21)
  - "A Report on the National Task Force on the Continuing Education Unit" (Turner, William L.), 1972 (Box 21)
  - "The Continuing Education Unit: A Proposal for a Statement of Criteria and Guidelines" (Turner, William L.), 1972 (Box 21)
  - CEU Criteria and Guidelines, 1973-1993
    - Drafts, 1973-1974; 7 folders (Box 21)
    - Drafts, 1974; 2 folders (Box 22)
    - 1st edition, 1974 (Box 22)
    - 2nd edition, 1979 (Box 22)
    - 3rd edition, 1986 (Box 22)
    - 5th edition (published by CCEU as IACET), 1993 (Box 22)
  - "A Plan for the Organization, Maintenance and Functioning of the National Advisory Council on the CEU" (Grogan, Paul J.), 1974 (Box 22)
  - "A Proposal to Implement the Council on the Continuing Education Unit and Identify and Describe Exemplar Applications of the CEU" (CCEU), 1978 (Box 22)
  - "A Prospectus for the Council on the Continuing Education Unit 1978-80" (CCEU/ETS), 1978 (Box 22)
  - The CCEU Reporter, 1979-1989; issues of the CCEU newsletter (Box 22)
  - "Position Paper on the Establishment of a National Certification System for Continuing Education Providers by the Council on the Continuing Education Unit" (CCEU), 1980 (Box 22)
    See also Correspondence-subject files: Miscellaneous [John Rhodes files] for Rhodes' annotated draft
  - "The Continuing Education Unit (CEU) Fact Sheet", 1981 (Box 22)
  - Standards of Practice in Continuing Education (CCEU), 1983 (Box 23)
  - Principles of Good Practice in Continuing Education (CCEU), 1984 (Box 23)
  - "Organizations and Institutions Awarding Continuing Education Units: A Partial List" (CCEU), 1986 (Box 23)
  - "Proposed Provider Certification Program" (draft) (CCEU as IACET)", 1990 (Box 23)
  - A Practical Handbook for Assessing Learning Outcomes in Continuing Education and Training (CCEU as IACET), 1991 (Box 23)
  - "How to Become a Certified Provider of Continuing Education and Training" (CCEU as IACET)", 1992 (Box 23)
  - Certified Provider Manual (CCEU as IACET), 1992 (Box 23)
  - Bibliography and references on the CEU, 1973-1996 (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous brochures, applications and announcements (CCEU), 1971-1996 (Box 23)
  - "The National Use of a Continuing Education Unit to Measure and Record Noncredit Continuing Education Experiences as a Factor in Productivity Increases Through Expanded Occupational and Professional Training Activities of Employers" (National Task Force), undated (Box 23)
- Papers and Articles
  This series is a mixture of xeroxed copies, reprints, typescripts, and originals from newsletters, bulletins, journals. Papers are ordered alphabetically by author; within a single author, papers are ordered chronologically.
  - About the CEU
    - American College Testing Program. "National Registry for Continuing Education", 1978 (Box 23)
    - American Nurses' Association. "An Interim Statement on Continuing Education in Nursing", 1972 (Box 23)
    - American Nurses' Association. "Draft Statement on Continuing Education", 1973 (Box 23)
    - American Nurses' Association. "Statement of Interpretation and Clarification in the Use of the CEU", 1973 (Box 23)
    - Andrews, Grover J. "One Model on the Use and Implementation of the CEU Within a University System", 1972 (Box 23)
    - Andrews, Grover J. "CEU Perspectives and Issues: Higher Education", 1979 (Box 23)
    - Australian Institute of Management. "Continuing Education Units will Provide Training Record", 1979 (Box 23)